<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>CSS on Katherine Wood</title>
    <link>https://katherinemwood.github.io/techs/css/</link>
    <description>Recent content in CSS on Katherine Wood</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© Katherine Wood</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 19:47:09 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://katherinemwood.github.io/techs/css/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Now or never: noticing occurs early in sustained inattentional blindness</title>
      <link>https://katherinemwood.github.io/publications/ib_timing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 19:47:09 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katherinemwood.github.io/publications/ib_timing/</guid>
      <description>Abstract People can show sustained inattentional blindness for unexpected objects visible for seconds or even minutes. Would such objects eventually be noticed given enough time, with the likelihood of noticing accumulating while the unexpected object is visible? Or, is there a narrow window around onset or offset when an object is most likely to be detected, with the chances of noticing dropping outside of that window? Across three experiments (total n&amp;rsquo;s = 283, 756, 488) exploring the temporal dynamics of noticing in sustained inattentional blindness, subjects who noticed the unexpected object did so soon after it onset.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The spatial allocation of attention in an interactive environment</title>
      <link>https://katherinemwood.github.io/publications/interactive_ib/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 19:47:09 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katherinemwood.github.io/publications/interactive_ib/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Inattentional blindness methods allow for an unobtrusive measure of the spatial distribution of attention; because subjects do not expect the critical object, they have no reason to devote attention to task-irrelevant regions in anticipation of it. We used inattentional blindness to examine the spatial allocation of attention in an interactive game in which subjects navigated through a dynamic environment and avoided hazards. Subjects were most likely to notice unexpected objects in the areas with the greatest risk of contact with a hazard, and less likely to notice equally proximal objects in inaccessible areas of the display or areas in which hazards no longer posed a threat.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing without noticing in inattentional blindness: A replication of Moore &amp; Egeth (1997) and Mack &amp; Rock (1998)</title>
      <link>https://katherinemwood.github.io/publications/implicit_ib/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 19:47:09 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katherinemwood.github.io/publications/implicit_ib/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Surreptitious online measures can reveal processing of stimuli that people did not report noticing or could not describe. People seem to glean everything from low-level Gestalt grouping information to semantic meaning from unattended and unreported stimuli, and this information seems capable of influencing performance and priming semantic judgments. Moore and Egeth (1997) provided evidence that judgements about the lengths of two lines were influenced by the grouping of background dots, even when subjects did not notice the pattern they formed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The role of similarity in inattentional blindness: Selective enhancement, selective suppression, or both?</title>
      <link>https://katherinemwood.github.io/publications/ib_similarity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2017 19:47:09 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katherinemwood.github.io/publications/ib_similarity/</guid>
      <description>Abstract When people selectively pay attention to one set of objects and ignore another, unexpected stimuli often go unnoticed. Noticing rates are higher when the unexpected object matches the features of the attended items and lower when it matches those of the ignored items. No prior studies have fully disentangled these aspects of similarity; in previous work, the unexpected object fell on a continuum between the attended and ignored objects, so increasing the similarity to one set of objects necessarily decreased it to the other.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Selective attention in inattentional blindness: Selection is specific but suppression is not</title>
      <link>https://katherinemwood.github.io/publications/ib_color/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 19:47:09 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katherinemwood.github.io/publications/ib_color/</guid>
      <description>Abstract When we selectively attend to one set of objects and ignore another, we often fail to notice unexpected events. The likelihood of noticing varies depending on the similarity of an unexpected object to other items in the display, a process thought to be controlled by the attention set that we create for the attended and ignored objects. It remains unclear, though, how attention sets are formed and structured. Do they enhance features of attended objects (“white”) and suppress features of ignored objects (“black”), or do they distinguish objects based on relations or categories (“darker” versus “lighter,” or “dark objects” versus “light objects”)?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>